她太让我害怕了
She scares me so much.
跟我一起数数
Just count with me.
奥地利 维也纳 1877年12月
VIENNA, AUSTRIA. DECEMBER 1877
多久?- 40
How long? - 40.
无稽之谈 整整一分十一秒，陛下
Nonsense. It was a whole minute and eleven seconds, Majesty.
获取Lotti
Fetch Lotti.
在奏完国歌的最后几小节后，皇帝和皇后到达
The Emperor and Empress will arrive to the last bars of the national anthem.
你们同时离开马车
You leave the carriage simultaneously
在新的艺术历史博物馆的正门前
in front of the main entrance of the new Museum of Art History.
迎接你们的将是建筑师巴伦·冯·哈森诺尔，
You will be greeted by the architect Baron von Hasenauer,
费尔德市长和奥尔斯佩格亲王部长兼总统，
mayor Felder and minister-president Prince of Auersperg,
他们将和你们一起参加封顶仪式
who will join you in the topping-out ceremony.
既然您有段时间没见他了，陛下请允许我说几句
Since you haven't seen him in a while, Your Majesty will permit me to remark
王子从一开始就对双重君主制持批评态度
that the Prince has been critical of the Double Monarchy from the very start.
他似乎对天数有精确的记录
He seems to keep a precise record of how many days
陛下在匈牙利的领土上
Your Majesty spends on Hungarian soil.
在皇帝的身边胜利了
At the Emperor's side prevails
他讲的是常识
He related by common sense
富有魅力，永不过时
Rich in charm that never outdated
我们尊贵的皇后
Our gracious Empress
这是多么幸运的事啊
What fortune to be praised as highly
从天空流下的小溪在他们身上
Stream from the sky on them
弗兰兹·约瑟夫万岁
Hail Franz Joseph
冰雹伊莉斯
Hail Elise
祝福整个哈布斯堡家族
Blessing to the entire House of Habsburg
威严
Majesty.
小心你的背，阿道夫
Watch out for your back, Adolf.
宏伟的建筑 你一定很骄傲，卡尔
A magnificent building. You must be proud, Carl.
就好像你的水墨画活过来了还跑到环街去了
As though your ink drawing came to life and made its way to the Ringstrasse.
多么难得的荣誉啊，陛下
What a rare honour, Your Majesty.
我妻子最近在报纸上看到你在与体重作斗争
My wife read recently in the papers that you were struggling with your weight.
这些小报真是个祸害
These tabloids are a veritable plague.
陛下，很高兴欢迎您的光临
Your Majesty, what a delight to welcome you in person.
作为一个欣赏艺术的人，我当然知道你的优雅的描述
Being appreciative of art, I know of course the depictions of your gracefulness.
幸运的是，有很多，因为在维也纳
Luckily, there are plenty because here in Vienna
我们几乎认为陛下是一个幽灵
we almost think of Majesty as a phantom.
你慢慢地往后晃，然后……
You sway back slowly and then...
然后是眼睛 在合适的时候，你这样做…
And then the eyes. At the right moment, you do this...
像这样，然后……
Like this and then...
这看起来不太对，路德维希 -那再给我看看
That did not look quite right, Ludwig. - Show me again then.
你让我想起了我的狗
You remind me of my dogs.
我很乐意做你的狗，那样我就不会让你丈夫这么生气了
I'd love to be your dog, then I wouldn't vex your husband so much.
你会 他嫉妒我的狗
You would. He's jealous of my dogs.
是吗?-是的
Is he? - He is.
但实际上,
But actually,
你让我想起了我的墙纸
you much rather remind me of my wallpaper.
他们悲痛欲绝
They were inconsolable.
他们偶尔想确认你的存在
They want to assure themselves of your existence occasionally.
我真的觉得……所以弱
I really felt... so weak.
那些颧骨 -他很可爱，不是吗?
Those cheekbones. - He is sweet, isn't he?
你亲爱的表妹还要待很久吗?
Is your dear cousin staying much longer?
他明天就要走了 他有义务
He is leaving tomorrow. He has obligations.
我从没见过比他更善变的人 -你没有吗?
I have never met a more fickle person. - Haven't you?
人们会说你又病了
People will gossip that you are sick again.
这确实让我恶心
Well, it does make me sick
站在那里，头上顶着一公斤锡，而所有人都呆呆地看着我
to stand there with a kilo of tin on my head, while everybody gawks at me.
你要怎么对付塞尔维亚人?久拉怎么说?
What will you do about the Serbians? What does Gyula say?
贝克将军和我一直有联系
General Beck and I have been in contact.
Andrássy的意见现在不重要了
Andrássy's opinion is of minor importance now.
我也一样
As is mine.
阻止这种情况的发生
Stop that.
看看匈牙利给我们带来了什么?——是的
See what Hungary has brought us? - Yes.
一个王国
A kingdom.
我当时问过你的意见
I asked for your opinion back then.
直到今日，我还因此被人藐视
And I am despised for doing so to this day.
“狮子不会因为羊的意见而失眠 ”
"A lion doesn't lose sleep over the opinion of sheep."
没有人爱任何人
Nobody loves nobody.
每个人都喜欢他想从别人那里得到的东西
Everybody loves what he wants from others.
我们爱那些在我们身上爱我们想成为的人
And we love anybody who loves in us that which we would like to be.
我们去旅行吧
Let's go on a journey.
陛下，还有两天就是圣诞节了
Majesty, it's Christmas in two days.
“由独立党组织的大型集会
"The large assembly organised by the Independence Party
有5000多人参加
was attended by over 5,000 people.
激烈的演讲反对部长Andrássy……”
Vehement speeches were held in opposition to Minister Andrássy..."
妈妈，树正在装饰呢 这是我们有过的最大的一次
Mama, the trees are being decorated. They are the biggest ones we have ever had.
你必须去看看他们 -我不太关心死掉的植物
You have to see them. - I do not care much about dead plants.
这孩子脸色苍白
The child looks pale.
是的,陛下 -你必须呼吸点新鲜空气
Yes, Majesty. - You must get some fresh air.
她最后一次出门是什么时候?-我有好多功课要做，妈妈
When was she last outdoors? - I have so much studying to do, Mama.
学习很好，但呼吸更好
Studying is good, but breathing is even better.
派人去找Hunyady
Send for Hunyady.
这孩子德文读得太多了 ——是的
The child is reading too much in German. - Yes.
一个年轻的理想主义者当然是没有概念的
A young idealist has of course no idea
贵族生活的职责和奉献
of the duties and devotion that mark the lives of the aristocracy.
但翻阅他的报纸还是很有趣的
But it's quite amusing to leaf through his newspaper.
我有时会偷偷做这件事
I sometimes do it in secret.
这一定是年轻人的大胆
It must be the audacity of youth
这给了他共和党的想法
that gives him these republican ideas.
这些报社的人对女王陛下非常迷恋
These newspaper people are quite infatuated with Her Majesty.
你妈妈总是能给你带来很多故事，不是吗?
She is always a source of stories, your Mama, isn't she?
我想说更多的是谣言
More of rumours, I would say.
愿她活得长久，愿她活得长久
Long may she live Long may she live
还有更多
And yet more so
愿她长命百岁
Long may she live
还有更多
And yet more so
愿她永远美丽
Beautiful may she remain
还有更多
And yet more so
蜡烛，妈妈
The candles, Mama.
呼吸平稳，像个20岁的年轻人
A steady breath like a 20-year-old.
敬你一杯，亲爱的
Here's to you, my darling.
生日快乐
Happy Birthday.
一个人在40岁的时候开始散去和褪色，
At the age of 40 a person begins to disperse and fade,
像云一样变暗
darkening like a cloud.
例如，我们打算把这两个部分，
For example, we intend to place the two sections,
对于平静的和焦躁不安的病人，
for peaceful and for restless patients, further apart,
一组人的情绪波动
so the emotional mood swings of one group
不要引发对方的歇斯底里和恐慌
do not trigger attacks of hysteria and panic in the other.
根据陛下上次来访时的宝贵意见，
And in line with Your Majesty's valuable remark on your last visit,
这让医护人员惊慌失措
which put the medical staff in a flurry,
正在考虑安装现代化的浴室
the installation of modern bathrooms is being considered.
尤其是自从温泉浴有了治愈的功效，
Especially since the healing power of warm baths,
在水里加入各种物质，甚至是电，
with various substances or even electricity added to the water,
在治疗中越来越重要
is proving of increasing importance in this treatment.
你好 紫罗兰蜜饯
Hello. Candied violets.
你会喜欢他们的
You will like them.
麻痹低能
Paralytic imbecility.
由继发性梅毒引发
Triggered by secondary syphilis.
你不记得我了吗?
Don't you remember me?
上次你说我很漂亮
Last time you told me I was beautiful.
这里的大多数女人生性忧郁
Most of the women here are by nature melancholic.
耶稣
Jesus.
一位仙女
A fairy.
瓦莱丽
Valerie.
来吧，穿好衣服
Come on, get dressed.
现在是晚上
It's night time.
我们要去旅行 就我们俩
We are going on a little trip. Just the two of us.
允许吗?-我允许，我最亲爱的
Is it allowed? - I allow it, my dearest.
来了
Come.
你的马睡着了 -我什么也看不见，妈妈
Your horse is falling asleep. - I can't see anything, Mama.
我好冷
And I'm so cold.
黑暗是美丽的 这是保护
Darkness is beautiful. It's protection.
瓦莱丽
Valerie.
“…看见一条大鱼扑打着翅膀，
"... saw a large fish flapping around,
被困在荆棘丛中，动弹不得
trapped in a thorn bush, unable to move.
鱼一看见赛普骑在马上，就对他说:
As soon as the fish saw Sepp on his horse, it addressed him:
上帝保佑你，请把我从这荆棘中解救出来
God bless you, please free me from this thorn bush.
我已经被困在这里七年了……”
I have been trapped here for seven years..."
超过40度?- 39
Over 40 degrees? - 39.
她很好
She is quite fine.
爸爸!
Papa!
我无法理解你竟然拿我们孩子的健康冒险
It's beyond my comprehension that you of all people would risk our child's health.
你会一直责怪我吗?
Will you always blame me?
我们不太了解它 我们就不该和索菲一起旅行
We didn't know it better. We should never have travelled with Sophie.
她可能也在这里生病了 ——不!——是的!
She could have fallen ill here, too. - No!  - Yes!
我不想把你的不安遗传给我们的孩子
I don't want you to pass on your restlessness to our child.
抚养孩子是我一个人的事
The task of raising the children is mine alone.
你在纸上做出了承诺
You committed yourself on paper.
我不相信你会在他们身上看到更多
I do not believe that you see more in them
比他们在王位继承中的地位更重要
than their position in the succession to the throne.
爸爸!
Papa!
你好,公主
Hello, princess.
她现在应该22岁了
She would be 22 years old now.
她一点也不滑稽，也不胖
She wasn't that droll and chubby at all.
但她的表情确实很严肃
But she did have that serious look.
他抓住了这口井
He captured that well.
至少我们留下了一张她的漂亮照片
At least we leave behind a pretty picture of her.
房间需要打扫了
The room needs to be cleaned.
我丈夫不跟我一起去吗?
My husband is not joining me?
陛下，我奉命只为您准备晚餐
I was ordered to serve your dinner only, Majesty.
晚上好，陛下
Good evening, Your Majesty.
陛下出去了吗?
Has His Majesty gone out?
不，陛下 陛下已经上床睡觉了
No, Your Majesty. His Majesty has already gone to bed.
他不舒服吗?
Is he unwell?
陛下身体很好，陛下
His Majesty is quite well, Your Majesty.
你屁眼儿
You arsehole.
原谅我这么晚打扰你 -骚乱越晚越好
Forgive me for disturbing you so late. - The later the disturbance, the better.
你走得太突然了 -我总是在新年后离开
You are leaving so suddenly. - I always go away after New Year.
我妹妹会和我一起去
My sister will be joining me.
爸爸很惊讶你…
Well, Papa is surprised that you...
不管怎样…我愿意陪你
Howsoever... I would like to accompany you.
可爱
Lovely.
现在他们在检查我是否变老了
Now they're checking if I've grown old.
英国北安普敦郡 1878年1月
NORTHAMPTONSHIRE, ENGLAND. JANUARY 1878
谢谢你！
Thank you.
贝永远不会娶夏洛特
Bay will never marry Charlotte.
你很清楚为什么
You know very well why.
你不想喝雪利酒吗?
Don't you want your sherry?
我看不出酒精有什么吸引力 -它有助于放松
I do not see the attraction of alcohol. - It helps to relax.
还记得爸爸喝了七杯啤酒吗?
Remember father after seven tankards of beer?
你夸大
You exaggerate.
我相信每个人在天黑后都是这样说话的
I believed every man spoke that way after dark.
晚饭后他讲话含糊不清
He slurred his speech after dinner.
我妹妹累了
My sister is tired.
是的，殿下
Yes, Your Highness.
殿下
Your Imperial Highness.
你的眼睛很好 -是的，我喜欢
You have good eyes. - Yes, I do.
陛下，路易·勒·普林斯先生，住在利兹
Majesty, Mr Louis Le Prince, resident in Leeds.
他要求见你 伯爵觉得你可能会对他的请求感兴趣
He asked to meet you. The Earl felt his request might interest you.
你有什么要求吗?-陛下
You have a request? - Your Majesty.
据说你对技术创新的兴趣对一个女人来说是不寻常的
It is said that your interest in technical innovation is unusual for a woman.
我要展示的是一项激动人心的新发明
And what I have to present is indeed an exciting new invention.
但你看起来并不兴奋 ——没有 我性情平和
But you don't appear excited. - No. I am even-tempered by disposition.
我想拍下你，陛下
I would like to film you, Majesty.
你想吃点什么?
What would you like?
我发明了一种能捕捉动态图像的装置
I have developed an apparatus that can capture moving pictures.
喜欢摄影吗?
Like photography?
不同之处在于照片不会移动
The difference is that photographs don't move.
我不太喜欢照片
I don't think much of photographs.
他们声称是客观的 但没有什么是客观的
They claim to be objective. But nothing is ever objective.
嗯…
Well...
对你的美丽和优雅的描述也不客观
the accounts of your beauty and your grace are not objective either.
但我现在知道它们是真的了
But I can now tell that they are true.
明天再来吧
Come back tomorrow.
好吧 谢谢你！
All right. Thank you.
晚安 ——晚安
Goodnight. - Goodnight.
先生，你的设备能听到我说话吗?
Monsieur, can your device hear me?
真是个好主意
What a wonderful idea.
但没有，唉
But no, alas.
不
No.
所以我想说什么就说什么，只要我微笑?
So I can say anything I wish as long as I smile?
是的,夫人 你想说什么就说什么
Yes, Madam. You just say whatever you wish.
你想说什么就说什么
Say whatever you want.
你父亲是怎么说的?
What does your father say about this?
他允许她做她想做的事
He allows her to do as she wishes.
但他自然会担心
But he is naturally concerned.
今天一个人吗?
All by yourself today?
不再是了 来，让我们一起骑马到森林的另一头去
Not any longer. Come, let's ride together to the other end of the forest.
我没有心情
I am not in the mood.
我得和你谈谈，妈妈
I need to talk to you, Mama.
你和你的骑术教练走得太近了
You are too close to your riding instructor.
贝不是我的导师 我骑得和他一样好
Bay is not my instructor. I ride just as well as him.
人们谈论你 我不想让爸爸听到他们说的话
People talk about you. And I don't want Papa to hear what they say.
如果你被流言烦扰，你就不是当皇帝的料
If you're bothered by gossip, you're hardly cut out to be Emperor.
你应该和他保持一定的距离
You should maintain more distance to him.
这不合适
It's not fitting.
我不会让我的孩子告诉我什么是合适的
I shall not allow my children to tell me what is fitting.
恕我直言，妈妈，是你表现得像个孩子
With all due respect, Mama, you are the one acting like a child.
你随心所欲，不考虑自己的地位
You abandon yourself to every whim, without considering your position.
你能毫发无损真是个奇迹 ——为什么?
It's a miracle that you are unharmed. - Why?
为什么我不能死而不是我的马?-这么说简直是亵渎神灵
Why can't I be dead instead of my horse? - It's sacrilege to talk like this.
他是最聪明、最强壮的马
He was the most intelligent and the strongest horse.
贝会给你另找一匹马的 -我不想再要一匹马了!我要我的!
Bay will find you another horse. - I don't want another horse! I want mine!
我再也见不到贝了
And I shall never see Bay again.
为什么?
Why?
有谣言说我们有外遇，让我儿子和我作对
Some gossip has imputed an affair to us and set my son against me.
我再也不想见到我妹妹了
I never want to see my sister again.
来点牛奶吗?
A little milk?
我们会帮你的
We shall help you with this.
你回来了 ——是的
You are back. - Yes.
奥地利 维也纳 1878年3月
VIENNA, AUSTRIA. MARCH 1878
没想到你这么快就来了
I wasn't expecting you so soon.
这件事之后我很忙 我以后来看你
I am busy after this. I shall come and see you later.
Blümlinger先生，我们会为您的家庭找到解决方案的
Mr Blümlinger, we will find a solution for your family.
你的妻子不应被迫成为洗衣妇 我们同情你
Your wife shall not be forced to become a washerwoman. We feel for you.
经过这么艰苦的旅行，你一定很累了
You must be very tired after the exhausting journey.
我听说你摔倒了
I was told about your fall.
很高兴看到你没受伤
Good to see that you are unharmed.
现在过来
Come over here now.
你可以别生我的气了
You can stop being angry with me.
我太老了，不能再要孩子了
I am too old for another child.
看着我
Look at me.
一直看着我
Don't stop looking at me.
艾达,亲爱的 没人在看，所以你今天可以试试
Ida, darling. Nobody is watching, so you could try it today.
不，谢谢你，亲爱的
No, thank you, my dear.
我命令你
I order you.
来了 世界上没有比这更好的地方了
Come. There is no finer place in the whole world.
不 -扶她上马
No. - Help her mount.
不,真的 ——是的
No, really. - Yes.
很好 抓紧了
Good. Hold on tight.
你的衣服
Your dress.
一，二，三
One, two, three.
好的
Okay.
我抱着你 好吧?——好的
I am holding you. Okay? - Okay.
不要害怕
Don't be afraid.
这是一匹温顺的马
It's a docile horse.
继续下去 得更快
Continue. Faster.
攻击
Attack.
现在!现在!
Now! Now!
和…来吧!
And... allez!
弯曲你的膝盖
Bend your knees.
前进
Move forward.
和背部
And back.
向前走两步
Two steps forward.
后退两步
Two steps back.
一个步骤
One step.
跃进
Lunge.
安娜·纳霍夫斯基，née诺瓦克
Anna Nahowski, née Nowak.
Schönbrunner大街8号的居民 18岁
Resident of Schönbrunner Strasse 8. 18 years old.
嫁给了弗朗茨·纳霍夫斯基，她的第二任丈夫 南方铁路的官员
Married to Franz Nahowski, her second husband. An official of the South Railways.
18岁?
18 years old?
她的第一次婚姻是与丝绸制造商约翰·休达克
Her first marriage to the silk manufacturer Johann Heuduck
是她父母安排的
was arranged by her parents.
Heuduck沉迷于酒精和赌博
Heuduck indulged in alcohol and was addicted to gambling.
他没能让她怀孕
And he was unable to get her pregnant.
他们说她模仿你的发型
They say she copies your hairstyle.
她很年轻 这比一个漂亮的发型更重要
She is young. That counts more than a nice hairstyle.
她的第二次婚姻也是基于经济原因
Her second marriage is also grounded on financial reasons.
她现在似乎渴望浪漫
It seems she is longing for romance now.
好像她和FJ在一起就能找到
As if she could find that with FJ.
汉妮，借我一件衣服
Hanni, lend me a dress.
陛下，我是菲尼
Majesty, I am Fini.
好吧，Fini
Well, Fini then.
还有一些蘑菇 不要太多
And a few mushrooms. Not too many.
我去买些肉
I'll get some meat.
你好 你丈夫好吗?-他很忙
Hello. How is your husband? - He's very busy.
我想要一些这个 你要多少钱?
I want some of this. - How much would you like?
它嫩吗?它必须是嫩的 -非常温柔，夫人 你自己看吧
Is it tender? It has to be tender. - Very tender, Madam. See for yourself.
让我试试 -当然可以，夫人
Let me try. - Of course, Madam.
精致的
Exquisite.
你应该接受它 你丈夫会喜欢的
You should take it. Your husband will like it.
谢谢你！好的 两份
Thank you. Okay. Two servings.
一个有经验的女人的建议是非常宝贵的
Advice from an experienced woman is very precious.
陛下，您脸色变了
Your complexion has changed, Majesty.
我经常在外面呼吸新鲜空气
I have been out in the fresh air a lot.
不，我不是这个意思
No, that's not what I mean.
别担心，我不会看的 我想要一个惊喜
No worries, I won't look. I want to be surprised.
结婚这么多年了，真是太好了
That's wonderful after so many years of marriage.
早上好，亲爱的
Good morning, my darling.
你抽烟了吗，菲尼?
Have you been smoking, Fini?
这是汉妮
This is Hanni.
不，亲爱的 这是Fini 汉妮更瘦
No, my darling. This is Fini. Hanni is skinnier.
我说的对吗，菲尼?
Am I right, Fini?
我们要和拉图尔和鲁道夫一起吃饭 他一大早就要动身去布拉格
We're dining with Latour and Rudolf. He is leaving for Prague early in the morning.
我们会长话短说，因为他的心思已经在旅途上了
We will keep it short, as his mind will already be on his journey.
正确的 继续前进，享受生活 再见
Right. Carry on and enjoy yourself. Bye.
你听说过电影技术吗?
Have you heard of the technique of moving pictures?
没有，陛下，恐怕我没见过
No, Majesty, I'm afraid I haven't.
它将取代油漆
It will replace painting.
希望不会，陛下
I hope not, Majesty.
让他们把家里挂着的我的画像都拿来，
Have them bring you all my portraits hanging around the house,
然后复制它们
and copy them.
还要注意我的肤色
And be careful with my complexion.
布拉格的学院组织严密
The academy in Prague is tightly organised.
我当然认识那里所有的绅士
And I know all the gentlemen there, of course.
我向您保证，陛下，我会留意鲁道夫的
I assure you, Your Majesty, I will keep an eye on Rudolf.
我很有信心
I am confident
为皇太子的军事教育找到了最好的地方
the best place for the Crown Prince's military education has been found.
你知道我的观点:纪律是必不可少的
You know my views: Discipline is essential.
但好奇心更重要
But curiosity is more important.
所以，睁大你的眼睛度过一生吧
So go through life with your eyes wide open.
你很年轻，布拉格是个美丽的城市
You are young and Prague is a pretty city.
积累经验，了解当地人
Gather experience, get to know the people.
好了，好了，老师 我希望你不是指那些年轻的女孩!
Well, well, Mr Teacher. I hope you are not referring to the young girls!
敬布拉格
Here's to Prague.
干杯,父亲
Cheers, Father.
你要走了，我很伤心
It breaks my heart that you're leaving.
我在尽我的责任，妈妈
I'm doing my duty, Mama.
别让爸爸伤害你
Don't let Papa hurt you.
我曾经给过你这样的建议
I once gave you that advice.
是吗?我想你自己也可以用
Did you? I think you can use it yourself, too.
爸爸对我们有他自己的想法
Papa has his own idea of us.
他不能接受其他任何想法
And he cannot accept any other idea.
紧
Tighter.
紧一点，我说 你手里难道没有力气吗?
Tighter, I said. Don't you have any strength in your hands?
星座说今天会是美好的一天
The horoscope says it's going to be a lovely day.
我在乎什么?艾达!
What do I care? Ida!
艾达!
Ida!
陛下吗?-我不明白
Majesty? - I don't understand.
他们现在去北极旅行，但仍然不可能找到女孩
They travel to the North Pole now, but it's still impossible to find girls
他们既能完成简单的任务又不会用他们的丑脸毁了我的一天
who master their simple duties without ruining my day with their ugly visages.
她尽力了，陛下
She gives her best, Majesty.
这还不够
Well, that's not enough.
紧
Tighter.
不要嘲笑我
Don't laugh at me.
你很清楚我比你强壮 -我是想让你高兴起来
You know exactly that I am stronger. - The plan was to cheer you up.
那你就得送我走一段很长的路
Then you would have to send me on a very long journey.
这太奇怪了
It's most odd.
你在这里想他，但你自己从来不想待在这里
You miss him here, but you never want to be here yourself.
如果你唯一的职责就是编辫子，你也会有同样的感觉
You would feel the same if your only duty was having your hair braided.
如果你想走，我不会挽留你
If you feel like leaving, I won't hold you back.
反正我很忙
I am very busy, anyway.
你不应该工作这么久
You shouldn't be working so much.
你应该时常出去散散步
You should go for a stroll every now and then.
Schönbrunn在春天很漂亮
Schönbrunn is quite pretty in the spring.
你的新肖像很可爱
Your new portrait is quite lovely.
我想知道你是怎么让自己看起来像个小女孩的
I wonder how you managed to look like a young girl.
你走后，它会让我想起你
It will remind me of you when you're gone.
我要带瓦莱丽一起去-我不知道
I'm taking Valerie with me. - I don't know.
不像你，她喜欢呆在家里
Unlike you, she enjoys being at home.
瓦莱丽的家在匈牙利 -你在投射，亲爱的
Valerie's home is Hungary. - You are projecting, mon coeur.
把她留在这儿
Leave her here.
看
Look.
你看到了什么?
You see?
幻景:产生运动幻觉的一系列连续的图画
A series of successive pictures that produce the illusion of movement.
人们会喜欢你的发明
People will love your invention.
我不知道 到目前为止…
I don't know. So far...
．.． 所有人都嘲笑我
... everybody just laughs at me.
真的吗?
Really?
人们害怕短暂的东西
People fear the ephemeral.
睫毛一眨，生命就匆匆逝去
A beat of an eyelash, and life has passed by.
他们会不惜一切留住它 不是吗?
They would do anything to hold on to it. Isn't that so?
你与众不同吗?
Are you different?
是的 ——如何?
Yes. - How?
我没有什么可以依靠的东西
I have nothing to hold on to.
除了我自己
Except myself.
有时甚至这看起来就像
And sometimes even that seems like
难以置信的努力
an incredible effort.
他不想见她 他刚派了医生来
He didn't want to see her. He just sent the doctor.
右小腿骨有轻微骨折 陛下，您真的有一位守护天使
A hairline fracture of the right calf bone. You truly have a guardian angel, Majesty.
把你的健康看作是上帝赐予你的礼物值得珍惜，陛下
Consider your health a gift from God to be cherished, Majesty.
巴伐利亚 1878年5月
BAVARIA. MAY 1878
我已经下定决心去死
I had resolved to die.
我只是没有足够的专业知识
I just didn't have sufficient expertise.
你喜欢呆多久就呆多久
Stay as long as you like.
也许是永远吧
Maybe forever, then.
那对你来说是不是太长了?
Won't that be too long for you?
没那么长
It's not that long.
给我一个橘子 切极薄的
Bring me an orange. Sliced wafer-thin.
真是个好主意 我也一样
What an idea. The same for me.
再来一小罐融化的巧克力和一碗鲜奶油
And bring a little pot of melted chocolate and a bowl of whipped cream.
很好，陛下
Very well, Majesty.
我才不管呢，我们可以吃四份甜点 其他的我不感兴趣
For all I care, we could have four desserts. The rest doesn't interest me.
你应该好好享受你的战利品，陛下 你开的枪比所有人加起来都多
You should enjoy your trophies, Majesty. You shot more than all the men together.
恕我冒昧，这对你也有好处
And it would be good for you, if I may be so bold.
你比画像上还苗条 -是吗?
You are even slimmer than in the portraits. - Am I?
这一切都是为了把我们变成甲虫，仰卧着，踢腿
All this is to turn us into beetles, lying on our backs and kicking our legs.
而是享受的能力
But the ability to enjoy
是人类文明的成就，殿下
is an achievement of human civilisation, Your Imperial Highness.
或者换句话说，我们是多么可怜的生物啊
Or to put it another way, what poor creatures would we be
没有好酒带来的愉悦和奇妙的放松效果?
without the delights of a good wine and its wonderfully relaxing effects?
用同样的方式来考虑欲望是不合适的，
It would be unfitting to consider lust in the same manner,
殿下
Your Imperial Highness.
所以请允许我醉一点
So please allow me a little drunkenness.
我羡慕你
I envy you.
真的
I really do.
张开嘴
Open your mouth.
这不是很令人欣慰吗?
Isn't it comforting?
原谅我，表哥
Forgive me, cousin.
我们是一体的，我最亲爱的 动物的本能永远无法与之匹敌
We are one, my dearest. The animal instincts could never compete with that.
所以关于马童的谣言是真的
So the rumours about the stable boys are true.
我爱你
I love you.
但你不想要我
But you don't want me.
你也不想要我
You don't want me either.
这只双头鹰真漂亮 ——事实上
Quite beautiful, this double-headed eagle. - Indeed.
但我觉得有点诡异 -你在奥地利有很多
But I find it a little bit eerie. - You have many of them in Austria.
庄园横跨那边的山丘
The manor stretches across the hills over there.
你觉得我们的地区怎么样，节日伯爵夫人?
How do you like our region, Countess Festetics?
或者我可以叫你玛丽吗?
Or may I say Marie?
我喜欢这里 它非常漂亮
I like it here. It's very pretty.
是吗?——是的
Is it? - Yes.
你的女主人介意我叫你玛丽吗?
Would your mistress mind if I called you Marie?
最有可能
Most likely.
你看起来不舒服
You look unwell.
你应该吃点东西
You should eat something.
我没想到你会这么平庸
I hadn't expected such banality from you.
原谅我 我把我的精神错乱遗传给你了
Forgive me. I have passed on my lunatism to you.
这不是你的精神错乱 我已经很久没睡了
It's not your lunatism. I haven't been sleeping for quite some time.
你想让我走吗?——没有 恰恰相反
Do you want me to leave? - No. On the contrary.
但请把你的寻死念头抛诸脑后
But please put that death wish out of your mind.
我想我可以和你分享
I thought I could share that with you.
我不许你淹死在我的湖里
I forbid you to drown in my lake.
这是我的湖
It's my lake.
反正我更喜欢大海
I prefer the sea anyway.
von Holnstein伯爵向我求婚了
Count von Holnstein proposed to me.
我知道你觉得他粗俗
I know you consider him coarse.
但他是一个英俊又聪明的人
But he is a good-looking and smart man.
有相当大的影响力和财富
With considerable influence and wealth.
他来自巴伐利亚
And he is from Bavaria.
这可能是我最后的机会了，伊丽莎白
It's most likely my last opportunity, Elisabeth.
绝不可能
By no means.
你是唯一爱这样的我的人
You are the only one who loves me the way I am.
奥地利 维也纳 1878年7月
VIENNA, AUSTRIA. JULY 1878
到这里来 我的宠儿 你好
Come here. My darlings. Hello.
亲爱的，你们好
Hello, my darlings.
到这里来
Come here.
我最亲爱的宝贝
My dearest darling.
我们很担心
We were concerned.
爸爸说你连自己都照顾不好
Papa says you can't even look after yourself.
她对我来说就像一本书
She is like a book to me.
每页上有一个谜语
A riddle on each page.
她的灵魂就像一个混乱的博物馆
Her soul is like a chaotic museum.
充满了无法挖掘的宝藏
Full of treasures that cannot be exploited.
她不知道该怎么处理这一切
She doesn't know what to do with all that.
她生活在一个不同的世界里，在那里她走着一条小路
She lives in a different world, where she is walking a path
窄到只能一个人走
so narrow that only one person can walk it.
夏天令人难以忍受 潮湿的空气也让你心烦吗?
The summer is unbearable. Does the humid air bother you too?
应该有人发明一种能把热量转化为冷空气的机器
Someone should invent a machine that turns the heat into cool air.
就像烤箱，但正好相反 那不是很棒吗?
Like an oven, but the other way around. Wouldn't that be marvellous?
恕我直言，殿下，这主意太棒了
With all due respect, Highness, an astounding idea.
我听说甚至还有女人发明东西
I heard there are even women who invent things.
当然
Of course.
你不希望平息关于你和Andrássy的旧谣言
You don't wish to put to bed the old rumour about you and Andrássy.
我只是希望我也能说话
I simply wish I was allowed to talk as well.
你关注萨拉热窝吗?-当然
Do you follow Sarajevo? - Of course.
但当我环顾四周，一切似乎都没有改变
But when I look around here, everything seems unchanged.
吃小龙虾，喝香槟，聊天气
Crayfish, champagne and conversations about the weather.
君主制正在衰落
The monarchy is in decline.
别让你父亲听到
Don't let your father hear that.
他知道我在想什么 他为此责怪你
He knows what I think. And he blames you for it.
你父亲相信上帝会把每个人安排在他认为合适的地方
Your father believes God puts everyone in the place He considers right for them.
上帝在我身上犯了一个错误
God certainly made a mistake with me.
我也是
With me, too.
现在谈话太早了
It's very early for a conversation.
我听说你根本就不睡觉
I am told that you don't sleep anyway.
什么事这么急?
What is so urgent?
掌控帝国的命运是我的职责
It's my duty to control the fate of our Empire.
你的职责只是代表
Your duty is merely to represent.
这就是我选择你的原因，这就是你来这里的原因
That's what I chose you for, that's what you're here for.
只要你喜欢漂亮的衣服和赞美，你就会喜欢它
You liked it as long as you enjoyed the beautiful clothes and the admiration.
但在分配给我们的任务中，快乐并没有发挥作用
But pleasure has no role to play in the tasks assigned to us.
我真的很累
I was really tired.
冯·威德霍费尔八点钟会到你的房间给你检查
Von Widerhofer will be in your chambers at 8 o'clock to examine you.
永远不要忘记，不管是支气管炎还是头痛，
Never forget, no matter if bronchitis or head-ache,
你是皇后
you are the Empress.
我为你的痛苦感到难过
I'm sorry that you are suffering.
我不知道该说什么，陛下
I don't know what to say, Majesty.
我真想抽根烟
I would kill for a cigarette.
请让一让
Make way, please.
FJ整天坐在办公桌前，抱怨工作量太大
FJ sits at his desk all day and complains about the load of work.
但没有关于数千名伤者的消息
But no word about the thousands of wounded.
请把电话号码给我
Get me the numbers, please.
我最亲爱的，你不该看到的
My dearest darling, you shouldn't have seen that.
我们让德梅尔送点东西过来
We'll have Demel send up something.
你还喜欢他们的奶油蛋糕吗?
Do you still like their cream cake?
妈妈，抽烟不合适
Mama, smoking is unfitting.
你让我很尴尬
You embarrassed me.
你现在怎么还能想到奶油蛋糕?
How can you think of cream cake now?
谢谢你！
Thank you.
久拉和你低估了占领的规模
Gyula and you underestimated the occupation.
嗯…
Well...
你来看望伤员真是太好了
It was very nice of you to visit the wounded.
有什么我能做的吗?-你已经做了很多了
Is there anything I can do? - You have already done a great deal.
关心士兵的命运对士兵来说意义重大
It means a lot to soldiers if one shows interest in their fate.
是的
Yes.
相信我吧
Confide in me.
你对萨拉热窝有什么计划?
What are your plans for Sarajevo?
我的印象是，那里的局势仍然不稳定
I have the impression, the situation there is still unsteady...
够了!
Enough!
你看匈牙利给我们带来了什么
You see what Hungary has brought us.
嗯，一个王国
Well, a kingdom.
重复也不会让我们的对话变得更好
Well, this conversation doesn't get any better by repetition.
你有什么愿望吗?
Do you have a wish?
我的心吗?什么都行
Mon coeur? Anything at all.
请允许我给你带来一些欢乐 告诉我你想要什么
Allow me to bring you some joy. Just tell me what you want.
一只孟加拉虎
A Bengal tiger.
或者扩建疯人院
Or an extension to the lunatic asylum.
你现在有足够的选择
You have ample choice now.
陛下，真想不到!
Your Majesty, what a surprise!
我喜欢和女人在一起
I like it here with the women.
浴缸送来了吗?
Have the bathtubs arrived yet?
她怎么了?-通奸，陛下
What's wrong with her? - Adultery, Majesty.
她看上去无伤大雅，其实是个十足的荡妇
She seems harmless, but she is a real hussy.
热水澡的温度大约是摄氏32度
The warm baths have a temperature of approximately 32 degrees centigrade.
使用时间长达25分钟
They are applied for up to 25 minutes
适用于各种形式的精神激动
and are indicated for all forms of mental agitation.
它们对整个机体有强大的舒缓作用
They have a powerful soothing effect on the entire organism.
她看起来好像想哭，但哭不出来
She looks as though she wants to weep but can't.
说得很好，殿下
Very well observed, Your Imperial Highness.
她出什么事了吗?
Did something bad happen to her?
她的一个孩子死了 但她还有三个孩子
One of her children died. But she has three others.
可惜的是，她不能从他们身上找到安慰
Too bad that she can't find consolation in them.
这是什么?-那叫海洛因
What is this? - It's called heroin.
半合成的阿片类物质这绝对是市场上的新鲜事物
A semi-synthetic opioid. An absolute novelty on the market.
它能抑制疼痛，有舒缓的效果
It suppresses pain and has a soothing effect.
我不疼 -这对你有好处
I have no pain. - It could do you good.
这是绝对无害的
It's absolutely harmless.
为了你的健康着想，我劝你多保重身体
In the interest of your health, may I advise you to take care of yourself.
在40岁的时候……
At the age of 40...
我可能会提醒你
I may remind you
40岁是女性受试者的平均预期寿命
that 40 is the average life expectancy of your female subjects.
皇后的避暑别墅 1878年8月
SUMMER RESIDENCE OF THE EMPRESS. AUGUST 1878
很好 一次
Very well. Again.
按这里
Press here.
玛丽
Marie.
今天晚上你不应该吃晚饭
You shouldn't have dinner this evening.
你是认真的
You're serious about it.
你已经把你的生命给了我
You have already given me your life.
玛丽
Marie.
在皇帝的身边胜利了
At the Emperor's side prevails
他讲的是常识
He related by common sense
富有魅力，永不过时
Rich in charm that never outdated
我们尊贵的皇后
Our gracious Empress
妈妈今天很严肃，是吗?
Mama is very serious today, isn't she?
她想念皇帝，公主
She misses the Emperor, Princess.
他以前过生日从来没有缺席过
He has never been absent on his birthday before.
菲尼!
Fini!
来了!
Come!
快 我们得解开胸花
Quick. We have to unlace the corsage.
把这个拿下来 -没关系
Take this off. - It's all right.
我很抱歉 -菲尼，来吧!
I'm sorry. - Fini, come!
快
Quick.
帮我……-对不起
Help me... - I'm sorry.
一切都很好 菲尼，打开前门
Everything's fine. Fini, open the front.
他们会说我胖了
They will say I have put on weight.
但他们可能会喜欢它
But they probably will have liked it.
你把它缠在一起了 把它给我
You're getting it tangled. Give it to me.
我一直在想你为什么要忍受这种事
I've been wondering for years why you put up with this.
艾达，你得给我称体重 我突然感觉失重了
Ida, you have to weigh me. I feel weightless all of a sudden.
首先，这个必须尽快送到维也纳的假发制造商那里
First, this must go to the wig-maker in Vienna as quickly as possible.
范妮，振作起来
Fanny, pull yourself together.
这是我毕生的心血
This was my life's work.
好了，现在你已经完成了
Well, now you have completed it.
多么感人的奉献啊 她很喜欢你的头发
What touching devotion. She has set her heart on your hair.
她很傻，但她对你有天使般的耐心
She is foolish, but she had the patience of an angel with you.
不!
No!
没有你的
None for you.
一周有三个橙色的日子
Three orange days a week.
晚上喝清牛肉汤 瘦肉，如果你愿意的话 仅此而已
Clear beef broth in the evenings. Lean meat, if you want. Nothing more.
没有土豆，没有面包，没有饺子 看在上帝的份上，不要吃糕点
No potatoes, no bread, no dumplings. And no pastry, for God's sake.
妈妈?
Mama?
进来吧，亲爱的
Come in, darling.
原谅我，妈妈
Forgive me, Mama.
没关系
It's all right.
妈妈，我想哭
Mama, I feel like crying.
但那是不礼貌的
But that would be bad manners.
但是妈妈!
But Mama!
让我抱着你
Let me hold you.
就像我的小鸡，最后一次
Just one last time like my little chick.
就好像你身体的一部分已经死了
It's as though a part of you has died.
留下来
Stay.
能被陛下邀请喝咖啡真是荣幸
What an honour to be invited for coffee with Your Majesty.
奥地利 维也纳 1878年9月
VIENNA, AUSTRIA. SEPTEMBER 1878
你认识皇帝
You know the Emperor.
这很有趣
It's funny.
当我见到他时，我以为他只是一个迷失了方向的普通士兵
When I met him, I thought he was just a simple soldier who had lost his way.
我想让你做他的情妇
I want you to be his mistress.
可以给我一些糖吗?
May I have some sugar?
据我所知，
According to my information,
你丈夫平时几乎不在家
your husband is hardly ever home during the week.
所以你会定期接见皇帝
So you will receive the Emperor regularly.
他……
He...
没有时间也没有耐心
has little time and no patience.
等着他在你床上，别戴胸花
Expect him in your bed, without your corsage.
和…
And...
和他谈谈
talk to him.
对他好点
Just be kind to him.
这是我非常关心的问题
It's a matter close to my heart.
你喜欢他，是吗?
You like him, don't you?
我遇见他的那天大概是…
The day I met him was probably...
．.． 这是我一生中最快乐的一天
... the happiest day in my life.
那我们就达成协议了
We have an agreement then.
这不会对你不利
It will not be to your disadvantage.
55.9.
真没想到啊，亲爱的
What a surprise, my darling.
你愿意和我一起吃奶油蛋糕吗?你要来杯热巧克力吗?
Would you like to eat cream cake with me? Would you like a hot chocolate?
我给你画了些东西，妈妈
I have drawn something for you, Mama.
那天你很有尊严
You were very dignified that day.
敏妮说你明天就要走了?
Minny says you are leaving tomorrow?
是的
Yes.
那你晚上应该早点睡 告别
Then you should have an early night. Adieu.
我们也可以等到明天早上 -走吧
We can also wait until morning. - Let's go.
安科纳,意大利 1878年10月
ANCONA, ITALY. OCTOBER 1878
陛下，我劝您到甲板下面去
Your Majesty, I must urge you to go under deck.
风越来越大了
The wind is getting stronger.
等一下，先生
In a minute, signore.